[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
hello this is justin baier for software
engineering radio and today i'm speaking
with jpm awesome
jp is co-founder and cso of tars jp is
known for his work in cryptography
including the reference book serious
cryptography
the widely used algorithms blake 2 and
sipash and talks at leading industry
conferences such as black hat and defcon
welcome to the show jp thank you justine
for the invitation
of course so just to start off the
episode i want to
lay kind of a foundational we're going
to be talking about today
so in cryptography there's generally the
two large
areas that i hear discussed encryption
and hashing can you kind of
do a quick discussion on what they are
how they differ
and a little bit on where you might use
one or the other yeah that's a good way
to start a discussion
so i guess you refer to encryption and
hashing
or signature i mean today crypto is a
very rich field with many different
protocols many different schemes
but as a software engineer most of the
time you would be concerned with
some form of cb3 encryption or public
encryption
and most of the time what you want to do
is encrypt some data or
be harsh on data so maybe fundamentally
the biggest difference is that
encryption will address confidentiality
or the data see our secrecy
whereas hashing is most often used
without the integrity of the data
so to ensure the data has not been
modified bit accidentally or maliciously
and there's a few differences depending
on the use case and the attack model
all right awesome so essentially we're
using encryption when we're
striving for things like confidentiality
and hashing is generally used in the
field of
you know data integrity and then there's
some overlapping crossover between the
two
with certain functions yeah so initially
the point of hash functions was to
protect integrity
but they ended up being like the swiss
army knife of crypto you can find them
pretty much
everywhere even inside random generators
and you can even build encryption
schemes
based on hash functions okay so
we are going to dive a little bit into
hashing and how fun
hash functions are created and where
that's used with encryption
but just kind of moving to a more
fundamental concept in crypto
i usually hear the discussion around
randomness being you know the big
you know base level foundation of all
things crypto can you kind of talk about
how we define and measure randomness of
data
maybe that's uh the most important thing
in crypto randomness like when i
give my crypto training you know the
first session is not about encryption
it's not about symmetrical public key
it's about randomness uh because
randomness if you don't have a good when
i'm generating crypto
then everything becomes predictable
therefore insecure
and the reason why is so is that all of
cryptography
tends to rely on some type of secret
usually the secret is a key or secret
key private key
however you call it but the secret key
must be a noun to the attacker
so a noun means unpredictable means
random
it means that at some point you have
generated a key using some
soldering time generator and you know
all your cryptographic scheme and
protocol
will bootstrap from this core randomness
that you had initially
so it's extremely important that you
have a secure prg in crypto
and maybe what's also important what i
tell my students
is that when you talk of uh something
random if you look at a string i don't
know zero one one zero one
you cannot tell if something is random
itself what is random is the
process that you use to generate
something okay and i usually
hear when people start to discuss
randomness the term entropy thrown
around can you kind of discuss
what that is how that fits into the
overall picture yeah yeah entropy is
maybe one of the most confusing terms of
crypto uh
you sometimes hear people you know
generating a string
an assorted a bit and say oh that's my
entropy you know because what i want to
say is that that's the random number
that i would use
um to get some predictability but
entropy
it comes from physics it comes from the
field of thermodynamics and it's just a
a way to quantify to measure the level
of uncertainty or randomness
so most of the time you want to have an
entropy level that is
as high as your security level so just
to simplify let's say you want to
generate keys of 128 bits
so you want a generator that has at
least this level of entropy
because in principle in theory if you
have a generator with entropy i don't
know l bits
then you can attack it by doing
approximately two to the power
and operations okay so essentially you
need the
level of security as kind of a
downstream effect
with that yeah but usually you don't
really have to worry about it
you're not going to measure the entropy
and actually if you look at how
linux is doing it they have a network
counter summaries
in dev brock somewhere i don't remember
exactly
but that can be quite misleading because
the way the confident trophy is
completely wrong
mathematically so you should not rely
too much on
what linux tells you in terms of entropy
yeah and you had mentioned it kind of
earlier
like with the concept of like a
pseudo-random number generator or prng
can you kind of discuss how that works
for something like in linux where i
usually hear the terms use like devran
w random and that controversy yeah so
you have different
ways to generate randomness on your
system
i think most operating systems will get
you random generator as part of the os
as part of the kernel
so if you look at linux it's accessible
using the dev slash random or dev
random device files and the way it works
is that the kernel
is running a system whereby you have a
state
a pool of like four gigabytes and it
would call it will collect data from a
number of sources that
behave fundamentally in an analog way
for example you know system interrupts
activity of your keyboard of your mouse
uh on the network and a bunch of logs
and it will combine all these data and
hash it and do a bunch of cryptographic
operations
and put all this data in a big table and
when you want to extract some randomness
then it will
take some of these data in these big
tables put it in some
deterministic random bit generator what
is called trbg
and from this you will derive a
potentially infinite
stream of bits and then again you can
access it using this device files by
using open and read
but the best way to do it on linux and
open bsc and freebsd
is to use the get random system called
which uh is maybe the safest way to
so why would i want to use the syscall
for example instead of going to dev
random or dev you random directly
so the cisco uh if you didn't see so if
you use another language like rust and
or go rgs you don't have to worry about
it but if you did
in c that's the base way because of the
following reason
a dev dom will block which means it will
stop returning data
if the linux uh kernel thinks that you
don't have enough entropy
but most of the time it will be wrong
you it could be good enough
dev uranum instead will never block
and specifically it will not block even
if you just booted the system
and you have never reached a state with
enough entropy and in that case you can
be in trouble because if you don't have
enough entropy like you know
one second after booting the system then
your
random data might be you know insecure
so what get random will do it
it will wait until the os has reached a
good enough level of entropy
and from that point it will never block
which is the right way to do
and you kind of handed towards this
earlier what are some ways that
prngs are attacked for example or rngs
for example are attacked you kind of
mentioned predictability but how would
someone go about determining that
one of these things is giving
predictable output yes
sometimes it's very you know difficult
to know if you have good randomness
because what happens you run an
application and you want to generate
some random stuff
so you don't necessarily just you know
return
the random buy that you get from your
prng sometime i know you want to
generate
a number with specific formats you want
to generate i don't know some
random image or random data structure
and you want to make sure that
all the stuff you generate is
distributed
uniformly which means that if you
generate a random number between i don't
know zero and four so
zero one two three or four i want each
number to have the same probability
of you know being returned by your
program and it's not always trivial
um because for example if you generate
random i take some example between zero
and four
you should not just take a random byte
and
you know the direction due to shot
modulo five because not on numbers
without the same
chance of occurring so what you want to
do is use in this example
you know rejection something just
specific techniques that you want to use
to generate
uniformly random numbers and you can
generalize this to
you know trading random stuff random
objects uh and maybe a second class of
problem that
i often found uh 10 years ago when doing
security of this
and i encounter much less often today
because developers know how this works
and you also have libraries using uh
i'd get you know strong rngs but this
problem is
that of using a weak prng so you have
two types of prng surrounded number
generators you have cryptographic ones
which are secure meaning that if you
have a long stream of bites
and you are no part of it you cannot
determine the rest
however if you have a non-cryptographic
prng uh like the one in
mass slash random like the one in the c
tele library i random what will happen
is that these they would be very fast
but they would be completely predictable
if you have part of the output so let's
say you generate one kilobyte you know
the first uh
i don't know the first six four bytes
then you would be able to determine the
rest
uh with something like the mersenne
twister but not with a cryptographic
quantity you want to make sure that you
use a stronger
prng so for example in a rows you want
to use rs rng
develop of course is a cryptographic and
that's a very common mistake
so just kind of changing directions a
little bit here now that we've kind of
laid the foundation of randomness and
how that impacts crypto overall
i want to kind of dive into encryption a
little bit now back in episode 378
uh there was a discussion about public
key infrastructure
and some discussion on tls and how the
protocol works overall
so we're going to kind of table that and
not really dive into that portion of it
i want to talk more about the
underlying functions of encryption and
some of the different
pieces of it so generally the term that
i hear brought up the most
in the world of encryption at least at
the base level is your ciphers and your
cipher suites
so can you kind of define and explain
what a cipher is
and what its goals are yeah so
ciphering is a very general term to
denote any algorithm
or in construction that gets you you
know this notion of encryption whereby
you take a plain text
and you obtain a ciphertext it also
applies marginally to systems that
include some type of authentication so
some types of signature
when we talk of cypher streets so that's
usually in the context of protocols such
as tls or ssh
where you can configure a system by
telling
the combination of the combination of
cyphers or
more specifically the combination of
crypto algorithm that you want to use
so for example in the other tls version
sentides1.1.2
you could say for example oh i want to
use rsa
for the handshake and then i want to
support um
you know ias cbc and rc4
and you would list your different you
know combinations of algorithms of
cipher strips in
specific order you know uh whereby the
ones at the top are prioritized compared
to the others but that's usually
i mean that's not for historical reasons
you know where you had systems spotting
different test algorithms
but today we tend to avoid you know
asking the user to choose what they
first they want because there's a chance
that they pick
the wrong combination of cyphers so if
you look at the score industry
you have very few cycle straights i
think four or five
or six and all of these are secure and
reliable and you know
you can shoot yourself in the feet most
of the time so
essentially as technology has advanced
and the world of crypto has started to
really be
more forefront on these common web
technologies
a lot of these things have been
abstracted out because again and we're
going to kind of discuss some of these
insecure safer suites later
you don't want the developer selecting
you know
triple des or rc4 as their encryption
algorithm
since we know it already has issues
even though sometimes you might if you
deal with some legacy system
you know you might not have the choice
uh if you want to communicate with all
devices laying around your company so
there are some cases where you want to
use them but just be careful
but just kind of changing subjects a
little bit so
i usually hear ciphers discussed first
and then i usually hear that there's
the two big giant groups of ciphers
stream ciphers and block ciphers can you
kind of discuss
what the difference between the two of
those things is how they kind of work
and then we'll dive into some examples
after we kind of discuss that base
yeah well typically today the good news
is that as a developer if you walk on a
web application or mobile app you don't
have to worry too much about you know
blockchain for stream ciphers
but historically uh they were from
two very different classes of um
applications
the stream ciphers the way they work uh
to encrypt a message
so you can see them as some kind of
scenario generator
what it means is that it will take a
secret key
and another value that we call the non
number used only once
and using these two values the stream
center will generate
a potentially infinite stream of solar
and unbiased so random looking bytes
and to encrypt you will just take this
random
key stream and accelerate with a plain
text and decryption is the same
because then you can cancel out the
keystream xr version
and the way it was designed it was just
a way to
simulate or emulate the one-time pad
which was
you know this system used during the
cold war
whereby you had you know a suitcase and
a very long string of base
and then you use you would use it only
once to exert a message with this
long sequence so block ciphers are
much closer to the intuitive notion of
encryption where you take a message and
you transform the message using some
crypto algorithm
and it's called block cipher because
it's actually
defined as an algorithm that takes a a
block so typically are
16 or 32 bytes and it transforms it into
another block of 16 and 32 bucks
but i mean we'll go back to this later
you can also combine the two and create
a block with a stream and a stimulant
blocker so
i mean yeah it's kind of less common
today that you're going to see this hard
delineation between the two because in
the protocols they eventually get mixed
together and
as you kind of mentioned we'll probably
discuss this a little bit later on in
the episode
but i heard you mention the stream
ciphers being like
a prng and you said that you use a key
in a nonce so is that similar to how
with a traditional prng you would
initialize the state
when you talk of prng for example the
synonym generator
in the linux system it's a combination
of different components
the one that will you know look for
synonym data from the environment the
system that will maintain a state
you know uh quite a big state of rocky
device for example
and the last component is
the one that is closer to a stream
cipher it's what we we usually call a
deterministic renovate generator and
this system behaves very similarly to a
stream cipher so it takes some input
value that is called a seed in the
context of prng
the context of three inside where you
would call it a a key
and that would generate a long stream of
bits but you can really imagine having a
surround generator system
where one of these components the last
one is very similar to a stream cipher
and if you look for example in the open
bsd um uh
kernel prng so it relies on charge
charger 20 uh oh with salsa one of the
two
to generate the randomness and this
charger 20 is exactly what you find in a
ts 1.3 as a string sector
okay so they're actually using a stream
cipher as part of their prng
and open bsd yeah interestingly
if you look at the core of charger 20 at
salsa is something that is very similar
to a
to a blog site where it's a kind of
permutation it's the same kind of thing
you find in the block cipher
and yeah now that you mentioned block
safers let's kind of dive into some
examples of what
are block ciphers or at least common
like block ciphers that
developers would see being used i
usually hear
aes being thrown around as the most
common one that everyone's using
and then the legacy being you know
triple des or dez which data encryption
standard
okay so most of the time you're going to
use aes
and sometimes you don't even have to
choose as because it will be the default
cipher in the library that you're going
to use
so it used to be a time where you had to
choose a yes after apple there sometimes
or something else
i think now most libraries have made it
easier for you
to use a as by default and the reason
why you want to use aes is not only
because it's the best cipher of all time
it
may not be but it's because it's
standard is supported pretty much
everywhere and in particular it's
supported
in your cpu as native instructions which
means that you have actual
uh silicone dedicated to running aes in
your chip
which method would be much faster than
another algorithm so for example
it would typically run at a speed of
like a few gigabytes per second
on a laptop for example and in
comparison if you
were to use abs without these
instructions it could be
approximately 10 times slower so that's
the reason why you use as most of the
time because it's
faster and it's safe okay so due to it
being built into the cpu it
makes it a lot faster and you know i
mean it is the advanced encryption
standard so it has been standardized and
i know nist has done documentation on it
and other things like that
but just diving a little more into aes
i've heard a lot of the underlying
functionality without going super into
the math here
it has like mixed columns and some of
these other functions would you be able
to explain like kind of how that all
fits together to create the encryption
standard yeah
so maybe instead of explaining
specifically how a
score works because we would talk about
finite fees and polynomials and
things that might get uh listeners a bit
a bit lost in math
you know when you design a site for like
aes and modularity when you design
something like a hash function or any
symmetric crypto scheme you don't design
a
a big algorithm that does those of
crediting
you want to minimize the code size you
want to minimize
the kind of stuff that has to be
analyzed in terms of security
so you will design a small piece of
transformation
that we usually call around and you will
iterate this round so in areas for
example you have 10 rounds
and then each round can be broken down
in four pieces
which each achieve a different security
property
so you have one one piece of around that
achieve what we call diffusion
which means it will spread the
differences all across the state
of es which is a 16 byte six by value
and you have another piece that achieves
what we call confusion
uh and corresponds to cryptographic
strengths by mixing based in a very
strong way
but not diffusing the changes across the
state and to achieve this we use
something called
s-box or some substitution boxes which
are kind of
tiny blocks at first that you use to
transform eight bits into another
eight bits inside a yes okay so it's
kind of back to that whole concept
encryption is all permutation and you
know kind of leaving the math out
specifically of aes
it's breaking things down into these
little boxes and then doing specific
functions on them to
derive certain security properties which
we are going to discuss a little bit
later
with security goals and security
properties of these algorithms
but i just want to jump back a little
bit before we had started talking about
block ciphers
i heard you mention modes of operation
can you kind of dive into what that
is and how that impacts how the cipher
works
yeah that's a great point because if you
take a cipher block sector alone
uh it's quite useless because it will
just transform one block of 16 bytes
into another block of 16 bytes but most
of the time
your messages would be longer than this
so how do you do the
very native way to do is just you know
split your message into blocks of 16
bytes
and then encrypt each block individually
independently of the others
so that's what the the mod called ecb
electronic code book is doing
but that's not a very secure mode
because
if you have two blocks which are
identical then the output block circuit
blocks would be identical as well so
nataker might be able to pinpoint which
blocks identical
in the plaintext that's usually
illustrated using the image of
the ducks penguin to see that if you
encrypt darts and each blocks
one part of ducks then the corresponding
images a bitmap will be
will have a similar shape uh so what you
want to do instead is use the mode
as it's a bit more advanced for example
the cbc mod set for blockchaining and
this has nothing to do with blockchains
it would just change the block by taking
the ciphertext of the first block and
doing an excel with the subsequent
blendtex block
and so on and you have another block
that another mod sorry which is called
the counter mode
and it's quite different it actually
doesn't
work on the message block so what the
counter mode is doing is
create a stream cipher based on a black
cipher and that's a completely different
approach
okay so essentially never use ecb
anymore if you can avoid it and then
you're looking at either a cbc or a ctr
mode when you're using something like
aes
yeah unless for this very specific case
uh when you encrypt small
very short pieces of data you know and
funny story we are doing a security edit
uh with
other people and my colleague another
cryptographer he
he tells me oh jp i found a critical
vulnerability
you know there you see ecb what a bunch
of video apps and i asked him i can
why do they encrypt pcb ah they encrypt
a pin of
four to eight characters say well that
fits in the block you don't need
a mod for this so that's the only
exception why is it is fine
yeah i'm sure there's probably somewhere
in the pci pin pad standard that ecb is
still acceptable for small data inputs
but as you kind of mentioned there so
we've kind of discussed these modes of
operation
and you mentioned how in a block city
for everything split up into these nice
little
blocks essentially of you know a certain
size 16 bits
so what do you do if your message
doesn't fit nicely into that
yes when you use the blocks you're going
to use the mod cbc or
the counter mode and maybe i can briefly
explain how counter mode is working
because it's quite interesting to see
how you can create a stream cipher from
any block cipher
so the way it works you are not going to
to split the message into blocks at all
you're first going to generate a string
of random base like you would do with a
string cipher
and the way you do it so your first
block will be
for example the value zero and you will
encrypt the value
zero with um what with your key and then
you're going to encrypt one you're going
to encrypt two and so on
uh as blocks of six invites and you're
going to take the result as a long
stream of buys
and then you're just going to exhaust
stream of bytes with
your message uh there's just one catch
here
if you encrypt multiple messages you
don't want to have the same stream of
bias
because it would be insecure so instead
you're going to use a a nonce number
that you're going to use only
you know only once for each encryption
instance and instead of just
encrypting zero and one and two and
three and so on you're going to encrypt
as first block
the concatenation of zero with your
notes right here
sometimes called an iv and this will
ensure that the
synonym string you're going to generate
will be different
for every message to be encrypted and
that's how the aes counter mode works
and that's how the aes
gcm mod works on you might be familiar
with gcm which is
the standard use pretty much everywhere
like in tls and
tls and ssh yeah so i've heard aes gcm
thrown around i believe it's the gloss
counter mode of it can you kind of talk
a little bit about
why you might use gcm mode
yeah so you have very good version to
your gcm gcm is not
just a an encryption mod it's an
authenticated encryption mod
which means that not only you're going
to encrypt the message but you're also
going to
generate a mac so messages on the
question call
some value that will allow you to verify
that the message has not been modified
the listeners might be familiar with
hmac hash based mark which is
a way to produce values that are you
know
symmetrical signature so to speak the
value that you regenerate and you
receive the ms section make sure it's
not been
it's not been modified so as gcm is
just a way you know a two-in-one
algorithm whereby you
both encrypt the message and generate
the stack so you don't have to combine
eh gcm with hmac
now with any mag flat purpose is doing
everything for you
and that's a much simpler way it's a
much more efficient way than combining
cbc and hmac for example
yeah and that's actually probably a good
point to start talking about hashing and
then kind of working into that
discussion on keyed hashing and how
that you know impacts things like these
authenticated hashes with
you know using hmac in combination for
aes gcm
so just to start off and set kind of
that base level
how does a hashing algorithm work i mean
you commonly hear like oh i'm going to
hash this piece of data for the purpose
of integrity
but how does that kind of work under the
hood so
i would say it's maybe the simplest type
of algorithm you can
you can imagine and you can design in
crypto because it's just about you know
taking a piece of data of
any size and from this piece of data are
producing
a value of fixed short size with
typically
uh 256 bits over the case of a chat
6 light 2 is kind of the same and the
wave cross underhood so
it's pretty much the same kind of
operations you're going to find in a
block cipher
so these operations where you mix bits
in a way that is
highly non-linear so in cryptography
nullia
usually means secure which means you
have a very strong
a very complex relationship between the
input base and hash function behaves
randomly but meaning that not uh
not meaning that it's probabilistic so
if you have twice some input you have
will have twice an output it could be
term it's deterministic
but it will behave in such a way that
you cannot predict
the output if you don't not input at all
so let's say i have two different
messages
and have only one bit of difference i
may not hash on the first one
but it will not tell me anything on the
hash of the second one because it will
be completely different
uh from the first hash so any small
challenge in the input we have a
complete you know a huge difference on
the output
so it appears in this kind of
unpredictable way that you need uh when
you build a mac for example
yeah and usually when i hear hashes
discussed
that there's two different families of
them a compression hash
versus a sponge can you kind of explain
what those are and how those differ
yeah sure so what you refer to is the
way you construct
the hash function internally because if
you look at how it works
uh when you're going to process a big
message you're not
going to directly read the message and
do something cryptographic with
this targeting message what you're going
to do instead is
like in a blog center you're going to
split the message into blocks
and you're going to process each of
these blocks iteratively
in your harsh function and due to
families you refer to
um i mean historically we build hash
functions using what we call a
composition function
so a composition function is like a hash
function but with a fixed size
input for example if you take the case
of a
charity five six it takes the one input
is what we call the chaining value
which is essentially the state of the
hash function
and it's sorted to solid device and it
will take in the second input which
should be the message block
and this message block will be 64 bytes
if you're not mistaken
and the output will be another certified
value
so you're going to compress a
combination of the state
and of the message block to get another
state value
and you're going to iterate this after
the message blocks so internally you use
something that is
quite similar to a block cipher the
other hash functions like chastry
they work a bit differently they rely on
something called a sponge
construction where what you use
internally is not
technically a block cipher but it's a
permutation so
block center is just a permutation with
a key and a permutation it's just a
black circle without a key
so ultimately it kind of relies on the
same types of you know b
twice worldwide transformation the
difference is that the permutation
is like a block cipher without a key
which means it's a bit simpler to design
it has slightly different security
properties there okay so essentially
when we're inputting a key into
something it's used as a way to almost
randomize the output in such a way that
you're not necessarily worried about
from a permutation perspective with
hashing
because you want the same input file to
result in the same output
versus with encryption you don't
necessarily want that
right that's just maybe one detail when
i said that you use a
block cipher in the construction of a
hash function the important details that
the key of the block cipher is not
secret
uh we use the key slot for example for
the message block for a chaining value
but it's not necessarily a secret value
because you can also construct hash
functions where you take a kia's
parameter
and that's a technique that you will use
to generate
a message artificial code or synonym
function
but the key will be processed a bit
differently yeah and now that you
mentioned that
message authentication code how does
that kind of
differ from the traditional hashing
where you know you're doing a keyed
hashing which as you kind of mentioned
that is the same for a compression
function no matter what
is it just that with something like a
keyed hash
you know doing h max you're doing a
secret key instead
so historically we wanted to to build
the kid hash functions to
to get marks to get pseudonym functions
and to use them as max
but we didn't have any and
cryptographers
thought about the idea of just taking a
harsh and instead of just hashing a
message
concatenating a key with a message or a
message with a key and then calling it a
day and having a prf
or a mac but they realized that this
native construction was not secure
in theory at least so they set out to
design something for which they could
have some nice mathematical proof
security proof that
this design fulfills all the security
goals you want to achieve
and they ended up with hmac hash based
mac
where you combine two hash functions and
this you have this nested construction
whereby
you compute the first hash and then you
hash a second piece of editor that
includes the first hash
so it's from my perspective it's a bit
over engineered
and historically we had hmac because we
wanted to have these security proofs
but now we have if you look at modern
hash functions like share three black
two or black three
you don't need the hmr construction so
you don't need to beat h max shot three
or h
mic blake's two of x3 because you
already have
a keyed mode designed specifically
with the hash function so it's used that
you do have
victory you can do it but you can
directly use the keyed version of big
two
which would be as secure as hmac okay so
as
time has gone on with most things the
way that we approach it is kind of
changing where hmac is
starting to get less important with
these
specialized functions whereas instead
you can use these more modern hashing
functions to achieve the same
security goals which we are going to
talk about a little bit later when we
start to discuss
how an algorithm is kind of proved out
and provable security and those concepts
but i just want to cover a couple more
things before we go into that discussion
so we've kind of discussed using hash
functions
and we've discussed them for data
integrity now i usually hear
the one common use at least is the
concept of hashing a password and using
assault
why would you want to do that what are
some situations in which you wouldn't
want to do that what are some algorithms
you would want to use versus not use
yeah that's a great point and maybe the
most important question in the
in the whole discussion i think what's
important here is that even if you have
a
secure hash functions just just free
black three
it might be secure in the context of
general cryptographic applications
might be collision resistant pretty much
resistant you name it
but you don't want to use this kind of
general purpose cryptographic cache
for hashing passcores and the reason why
it is is that
cryptographic hashes that are designed
to be fast because most of the time
that's what you want you want speed you
want to
you know protect product environment and
do as few competitions
as possible but in the context of
passports it's quite different because
the stuff you're hashing passwords
they have low entropy so if we we want
to refer to entropy again
and it means that if the hash function
is very fast very efficient
then an attacker that knows the hash
then they might be able to brute force
your password by trying many potential
passwords repeatedly
so what you want is instead is something
that we call password hashing function
and it's designed specifically for the
use case of passport
where you want the hash function to be
relatively slow and also to use some
you know fair amount of memory to make
password cracking much harder if you
have a gpu fpg or
another specific device so what you're
going to use instead is
something like dbktdf2 which is a the
knee standard for key derivation
so it's been called t derivation which
is quite similar to password lashing
and now we have modern uh algorithms
such as argon 2.
so i'm ubuntu was designed specifically
to be
secure against uh gpus and fpgas
and the way it works is that it takes
not only password it takes another value
that we call assault
so for each password you're going to use
you
want to use different sort and it also
comes with two different
uh two additional arguments so one for
the speed how many iterations you want
to do
how slow you want the the hash function
to be and the last argument is the
memory is edge
because you want to make the function
not only slow but to
force the competition to use for example
10 megabytes or even 10 gigabytes of
memory
to make it even harder to crack by
password hashing
password techniques okay so the
discussion around
using these key derivation functions
with salts and such the goal is to get
one an algorithm that's hard to
brute force easily and two using the
salt kind of gives you that
pre-computation resistance where someone
can't pre-calculate an entire table of
hashes and then kind of just match the
two
up yeah exactly that's a great summary
you're going to
use assault because otherwise the
attacker
knows an advantage which function you're
going to use
so they know in advance that if you hash
the password one two three four you're
going to end up
with a specific cash value so the salt
is just a
simple way to simulate the use of
different hash functions
because instead of using i don't know
chai one shot two sha-3 you just have to
have it to use different sort and the
hash function will behave completely
differently
which means that the attacker doesn't
know in advance uh what he's up against
to
so now that we've kind of laid this
foundation we've discussed encryption
we've discussed
hashing and we've kind of hinted to it
throughout the show
i want to kind of start talking about
security goals and how we actually
validate
algorithms as cryptographically secure
and valuable
so can you kind of discuss
the difference between the view of like
informational versus computational
security
in cryptography yeah sure maybe one
example
is maybe to the simplest one hash
functions
so let's say i have some piece of data
some passphrase i want to harsh and i
have to pass phrase and i give you the
hash
and let's say you have plenty of fan of
time on your hands you even have you
know
infinite time and you have infinite
computing powers
so the question is can you can you
recover my
password or the pass phrase i hashed and
the answer is no
because by what we call the pigeon hunt
the pigeonhole principle
since there are many more possible
different inputs to the hash
than possible outputs then there will
there would be for each possible output
many different inputs so even if you
have
infinite computing power you're never
going to find the input
that i use unless you know what how it
looks like so that's what we call
informational security which is security
even the even if the attacker has you
know an infinite amount of
computing power and infinite time and
competition competition security is just
a way to say that
okay if you have infinite computing
power you might find
a solution to my problem but in practice
you will need to carry on i know a huge
amount of competition that will take you
millions of years
so we just accept the race can we say
it's secure
so maybe i can briefly explain what it
means in the context of
of encryption so i think in encryption
you know use a key of 128 base
so you can of course try all the
possible keys
but it will take you you know
you will need to iterate over 2 to the
power 128 possible keys
uh which is a an umbrella um
trying to think of a comparison but i
think there's been only two to the
eighty also to the ninety something
nanoseconds
since the creation um since the big bang
like forty year
million years ago so that's a quite high
amount of competitions
so essentially it all comes down to
you're kind of taking two views of an
attacker they either have
infinite computing or you're kind of
looking at it from the realist point of
view where you're saying
realistically no one has infinite
computing power
what's the limit that someone would need
to get to to actually be able to
successfully break this algorithm
yeah so usually we consider that 128
bit of security is enough so generally
120 security just means that you need to
carry out of the order of 2 to the 128
operations whatever the operation is
so if you look at aes with a key of 128
bit then you're fine
if you look at any curve cryptography
with a
hk of 256 bits then you will get 120 bit
of security
one big difference is rsa so of course
if you have an rs key
of 1024 bit you're not going to have
1024 bit of security you're just going
to have
a key size a key of this size but the
security level we
will be much lower so for example
what you get with rsa 1024 is
i think close to approximately 80 bits
of security or even lower
i think it's much lower than this so you
don't want to use rsa1
1024 you want to use 2048 at least
okay and that just has to do with how
the underlying mathematics
of the algorithm and key derivation are
occurring it's just the fact that
rsa with the nature of it it's not a
direct correlation like it is with a
symmetric algorithm
yes completely different so a key size
for a key for a string cipher or a block
cipher is just
any any string you know of them of the
size
of the prescribed key size but if you
take the case of
you know rsa for example the key is not
any string is a
specific type of number with specific
properties so specifically prime numbers
it's not any value of the size
that you use would be a valid uh would
be a valid
valid key and the best attacks
to break rsa and the best attacks to
break um to break any care of crypto
so they're not they're not just no
brutal slag attacks there are attacks
that really
exploit the mathematical structure of
the algorithm so
if you want to break rsa you don't trust
all the signal numbers you
you try something much smarter which is
called the number of ec
so why do you want to use something like
elliptic curve over something like rsi
yeah that's a very good question and
then there's been a lot of debates in
the crypto community are rsa
vs elliptic curves so they're quite
different you you cannot do
exactly the same kind of thing rsa gets
you encryption
and signature which means encryption
then again you have
10 tags and you do the rs3 version and
you end up with a ciphertext
so you cannot do this with elliptic
curves elliptic curves can be used
to encrypt stuff but indirectly
essentially you would do a kind of
diffie-hellman and then you would use a
share secret to encrypt the
message you want you want to encrypt so
both rsa
and elliptic curve crypto can be used to
complete signatures
uh but with a big difference so with rsa
use you know private key in public key
and to sign a message
you use this privacy operation which is
much slower than the one you would do
with elliptical crypto
however the verification time when you
verify the signature
it's much faster with rsa than with the
ticker standard like ecdsa or
ed25 or 19. so if you really care about
signature verification speed and if it's
really important uh
in a product then you might prefer to
use rss signature than
a ticker signature but what we see you
know in most applications is
ecdsa d-curve etc signature you know
for example blockchain applications it's
all led curves okay
each of them gives you different
benefits of speed and cost
depending on what functionality you're
trying to use with the algorithm
yeah and in both cases you have to be
very careful to the parameters you use
the kind of key you use and you also
want to pay attention to sectional
attacks it's actually
it's about exploiting you know some
information some physical information
such as the execution time
and in both rsa and elliptic curve if
the action time depends on the private
key then you have you know
quite powerful attack that will you know
that you can reuse that we can use to
for signatures or to directly record a
private key
okay and we're going to actually kind of
discuss it when we start talking about
black box and gray box attack models
but just before we get there can you
kind of discuss
how an algorithm in the crypto community
gets proven as secure
so bracket news we never actually
literally prove the security of an
algorithm we just prove that when
algorithm is
at least as hard as breaking
another algorithm or at least as hard as
solving
a math problem that we we hope
we believe to be hard enough so like the
factoring problem
for rsa or the discrete algorithm for
dfellman and for the ticker of crypto
or sometimes you know the marketing
department
goes a bit overboard and they say oh
this has been proven secure
whereas in reality what's been proven
secure is just
let's say one type of attack on one or
one specific security option
so in the case of um symmetric
cryptography
you already have you know full-fledged
security proofs uh
most of the time we just rely on the
failed attempts
by many cryptographers for many years
but since we don't have this
mathematical structure that you have in
rsc or ift curves
you have no real way to to proof stuff
because it's
complete mess you have a very complex
relation between the input and the
output
but you don't have a mass structure such
as no exponents finance field and stuff
that you can leverage to to say
something about the security
and that's what you have in addition of
crypto and
and then again you might have a proven
paper but your system might end up being
completely broken in practice because of
software
work because of bad parameters
so it can be a bit disappointing to say
oh have this probably secure surprise
but then in practice it's a completely
different game yeah traditionally i hear
the example
of things like elliptic curve where if
you select a bad curve or a non-secure
curve it defeats the entire purpose of
the algorithm even though you might have
a
provably secure algorithm it comes back
to implementation and the parameters
that you're using for it
yeah totally does the type of query you
want to use so
the first thing you learn at the
elliptic curves code is not to design
your own curve
and you say standardized curve so don't
negotiate the curve parameters
and even then i think uh last week i
looked um
at a very nice article about um one of
the
most widely used uh t curve based
signature scheme called ed25519
which is a state-of-the-art initial
scheme based on the the g2519
which is safe and it's really already
reliable it's pretty much everywhere
but if you look at the standards uh if
you get different specifications
they will tell you different things
regarding testing regarding
input validation and in this article
they i think they looked at maybe five
or six different implementations
and all the implementations behave
differently
in terms of input validation and what
type of key authorized what
what type of signature you're trying to
be verified so you have to be also very
careful um
when you validate inputs and because you
have
specific public keys that you shouldn't
that should not be used so if you
receive a public key
you want to verify that you say value
and otherwise
you might end up with uh let's say in
signatures that will be accepted when
they should not be accepted for example
it's kind of again as we've discussed
already that implementation and
i'll definitely link that article in the
show notes and i'll also link
some information on how we discussed
earlier with the number field sieve
but just kind of changing a little bit
of directions here you've mentioned the
concept of security notions
and we've kind of discussed you know
side channel attacks and i mentioned
attack models before
can you kind of talk about what attack
models are
and black box versus gray box yeah
sure typically the when we prove
security of a cypher on when we make a
security claim
it's like you design a cipher you don't
just say oh it's secure
you say it's secure with respect to this
security goal
against this type of attacker and when
we say type of attacker we have
well-defined
attack models so in the context of
encryption
uh maybe the weakest the weakest
attacker you can imagine is the passive
attacker
that only sees cyphertex that's what we
call non-ciphertext or cybertext only
model
but in practice you know a real attacker
typically
they can inject content they can modify
content they can draw packets on the
network so you're dealing with active
attackers
and two model active attackers we have
um different options you have what we
call chosen cipher texts
so chosen cipher text is a kind of
article that we imagine has access to a
black box
and this black box will give them a
cipher text for any
plain text that's sent to the box so
they can send any number or you know any
reasonable number of plaintext and they
will get a separate tax
so in practice you might not have access
to such a black box because you don't
have access to the key
maybe there's some red limiting other
system maybe you don't view ciphertext
maybe you
only do part of it but if you can
produce your ciphertext
is secure in this context then it will
be secure in any
model where the attacker has less power
than um
a full you know just plain text oracle
and there's an even
stronger model that we call uh cca
chosen ciphertext attacker
so this one makes little sense to people
who are not familiar with cryptography
because they're like
well if you can decrypt any ciphertext
so if you have this black box that
to which you can send any cipher text
and get the plain text then
what's the point of you know attacking
the site for a tool because you can take
her to the
message you want so that's right that
makes a lot of sense and
but you have some cases where for
example drm where you can't decrypt
you may be able to decrypt what you want
but what your
what you're after is the key itself it's
not just the decryption capability
and then again if you can prove cipher
secure in this very strong model of
active attacker that can decrypt
anything they want
then it gives you a pretty high level of
assurance in the context where the
attacker has less
less capability than this but what about
if an attacker let's say is
able to compromise that key let's say
that they do defeat your cipher
how do you prevent them from being able
to then
decrypt everything going back in history
yeah i mean
interestingly if you look at for example
messaging protocols like what you have
in signal
what you have in whatsapp which is
pretty much the same thing
you make the assumption that at some
point the attacker might have access to
your device
or the attacker might have access to
some of the keys that's used to encrypt
the messages because in a protocol like
signal so each single message
is encrypted using a different key so
now you have this notion of backward
secrecy
and forward secrecy which are quite
different so
for our secrecy is about ensuring that
if the attacker has access to your
system to your
current keys then they will not be able
to
decrypt the past messages and they will
not be able to compute the previous keys
so that's for example achieved by
rotating keys uh
for example by hashing the previous key
and getting another key and so on
so backward secrecy backward security
which is also called
sometimes post compromise resistance or
future secrecy
is a bit different it's like the
opposite and much harder to achieve
so it's about making sure that another
girl that had access to your device it
had to compromise your system at some
point
uh maybe they got a snapshot at time t
of your system
then you don't want them to be able to
predict the future keys in your system
and that's achieved quite differently in
for example if you have a full
compromise of your signal
or whatsapp state then in theory
you cannot achieve you cannot achieve
this kind of security notion you need
some
different assumptions but then that's
quite different from what
we discussed before intcp and this is
here so that's security of a protocol
vs the security of uh of an encryption
schema
okay so when you hear those things like
perfect forward secrecy
or as you kind of mentioned you know the
reverse of that
those are more about the actual protocol
implementation of something versus
what we're talking about where you have
you know chosen ciphertext attacks or
known plane text attacks or what have
you
where you're actually trying to defeat
the underlying cipher
yeah totally if you look at this
relatively simple
case of you know message encryption it
it looks quite simple
you know i send you a message you send
me a message i mean how
complex can it be but if you look under
the hood it's terribly complex you
you have a symmetric encryption scheme
you have the fieldman and you also want
to manage the case where
you know so you make the assumption that
you have you know going to delivery and
in all of delivery but
at some point one party must be offline
maybe offline so you have to kind of you
know cue the messages
and make sure no message is lost and you
have to you want to some extent the
guarantee that
you would decrypt messages in the same
order as the other party
uh so you have a lot of things to to
deal with and it's
pretty complex crypto protocols and in
turn it also means that proving the
system to be secure
against three attackers is also quite
hard yeah because there's so many moving
parts it's kind of hard to just
say well this big number math problem
that we know is hard
is you know why this whole algorithm is
completely safe
whereas it's more about how they
interact with one another
yeah totally and that's what we call
composition in the context of crypto so
you might have you know
a piece one that is secure these two
that is secured individually
but when you combine them then uh yeah
because of some
interruption with your two protocols the
combination is not as secure as what
what you would expect and i think one of
the tools
used to to prove the security of this is
the
family of formal verification techniques
which are kind of mathematical proof
that your protocol
under some reasonable assumption will
behave in a in a secure way and we have
this kind of proof for example for the
signal protocol
okay and i'll actually try to get some
documentation and include that in the
show notes in case there's any listeners
that are interested
but we've kind of discussed security
goals a little bit
can you kind of dive into some examples
of what those might be
yeah great part i was thinking about it
uh actually so we we talked about
security in the cphs and
self-reflections on planets but what
does it mean to be secure
uh so maybe the intuitive notion is that
you should not be able to
recover the message from the plaintext
from the ciphertext but more recently
how do you define this
in mathematical terms so the definition
that cryptographers use is
what they call chosen other what they
call
semantic security which is technically
the same
as what they call indistinguishability
in the chosen plaintext attacker model
but to explain this in very simple terms
what i just mean is that
if you see a cipher text and even if you
can do chosen plaintext queries
the attacker should not be able to
determine any single bit
of the plaintext what you should only
learn is the approximate size of the
message that was encrypted because the
cell vertex is approximately the same
size as the plaintext
but otherwise they should not be able to
say anything about
how the plaintext looks like uh if it's
you know only zeros
only once and that's why it's called
indistinguishability because
the way we formalize it is by saying
that
ciphertext encrypted messages should
look
the same as random values so we proved
that
an encryption scheme is secure by coming
up with a mathematical proof that sales
protects are indistinguishable
from truly purely random numbers very
random values
okay so it's kind of that almost that
entropy discussion again but
instead you're talking about whether
there's a relation
between the actual plaintext prior to
encryption and the plaintext after
encryption
yeah totally and if you look at the
whole point the whole
security of symmetric primitives so we
talked about this you know
fancy notions semantic security uh
chosen cipher text you name it
but ultimately what you want to have is
a transformation
that behaves completely randomly that
behaves like if you are taking a random
function
from the set of all possible functions
and
if you talk in terms of you know
mathematical notions
it means you should have no correlation
between the input and the output
in terms of a physicist you should have
no no symmetry which means that there
should be no single property in the
input
that should translate in another
property in the output so it should be
completely random
but the flip side is that because you
have such a property of something that
behaves in a
completely random chaotic way uh so you
have no
no structure that you can exploit to
prove it formally
to preformally that it's a hard problem
so the listeners might be familiar with
the class of
heart problems known as np complete
problems
but you will not find you will not find
np complete problems in block ciphers or
string ciphers
because they don't lend themselves to
this kind of analysis
okay so essentially these symmetric
primitives they're a lot harder to draw
these direct math correlations to them
okay so kind of moving into
a discussion on some active breakage of
these
ciphers can you give some examples of
some of the common attacks that
you see against different ciphers like
block
and stream ciphers and even hashing
algorithms
so usually when we talk of you know
security failures with
this kind of algorithms i don't think
i've ever seen
a symmetric algorithm being broken in
practice
in really a really you know realistic
scenario where it was broken by
exporting a flow in cipher
most of the time and what we see i mean
all the time what we see fairly
frequently
is either bad implementations or
keys that have been fully generated for
example last
last week i found a
cryptocurrency wallet that was using a
yes and you know
key on the right size uh a good
implementation of a yes
but the way the key was computed from a
password was
quite quite weak and you could broadcast
the password and therefore determine the
key
so that's the kind of thing that we find
uh another example is uh when you use
aes gcm or where you use a stream cipher
like charger 20
you want to say a key has a secret
parameter
and also a nonce that is a valid unique
for each um
each time you encrypt a message uh so
unique of course means it should be
it should be different but what we
sometimes observe is that this nonce
is hardcoded and hardcoded in the source
code which means it's it's not unique
and then it's it defeats the purpose of
using a stream cipher
so yeah the option is that what you
should be careful is uh
less than the name of the algorithm you
use is how you use it how you generate
the key how you generate parameters
and also how you how you test the whole
thing okay so it's that implementation
issue that's occurring
and that it's kind of back on the
developer to appropriately test
their code and we can discuss that a
little bit later on
but as you kind of mentioned the nonce
you know or initialization vector iv
being hard coded
it reminds me of the zero log on
vulnerability pretty recently from
microsoft where they had a hard-coded iv
of all zeros
and i mean it kind of goes to show that
even these huge companies are making
these kinds of
oversights and mistakes in their code
but an initialization vector an iv
and a nonce are actually kind of two
different things and i hear them used
interchangeably a lot
just for the listener can you kind of
clarify exactly what they are and what
the difference between the two is
yeah you're right both terms are used
but you know they're quite different
so iv is sometimes called initialization
vector or sometimes iteration value
so the main difference um in the context
of
encryption is that an iv if you look at
cpc
for example the cpc mode the security
requirements that the iv should be
unpredictable
unpredictable which essentially means
random that nataka cannot predict the
future
the future ivs and the nodes is quite
different
uh norms is a number used only once uh
in the context of crypto at least
so why just means that you should not
use twice the same
value uh as long as you use the same key
so it doesn't have to be random you may
just use a counter like you know one two
three four five or you can start from
any like that you want
and you don't want it to repeat so if
you use a a random
random nonce so you might be fine but
you just have to be careful um that the
note should be should not be too short
because let's say you use a a norms of
64 bits
and you take a random value each time so
on average you will
you have a repetition of a nonce after
two to the 32 instances
so you should only use the random notes
if the nonce is large
enough so typically if it's 128 bits
you you should be good after at least
264 instances
but what you're need here about is
uniqueness not not randomness
okay so is there like a recommended way
that you would want to generate nonsense
so what you can do if you're in a
protocol
where you have different packets and
each packet has a
unique sequence number then you can
directly use the sequence number of the
packet as a non so you don't have to
generate and worry about
how to manage nones and you know that
the receiver of the packet they will
they will know the sequence number so
that you don't have to transmit
the nonstick separately okay because you
know it's equal to the sequence number
and that's pretty much uh
what uh what t-less on the street's
doing now so then
kind of moving along here how would a
developer
pick what cipher or mode or hashing
algorithm they should be using in their
application
so ideally if you use a
a type of api of library that
people call modern you you will have a
function for example
that would be called encrypt or crypto
box where you don't even have to choose
the
underlying uh algorithm you don't even
you might
not even know which one it is um so i
think a library like lip sergeant
gets you a a function called cryptobox
or crypto secret box
and you just give it a key and a message
and it takes you off everything for you
however it might not always be the case
you might have to choose which
algorithm to use or you might have to
choose you might have to use specific
algorithm because you must implement
specific protocols
or you might have to you might
your system might only support i don't
know a yes in
cbc mode so what you want to pay
attention to
is the key size is how you generate the
key
is the mode don't use ecb but if you
have the choice
of the library what i usually recommend
is to choose the library that
does part of the work for you so you
have library like for example an
um crypto plus plus or bouncy castle
where you have like you know huge choice
of algorithms
secure ones and less secret ones so if
you have the choice
better pick a library like salt or
sodium um
where you have little shots of
algorithms and
wait on your first you know good modern
uh algorithms and not all stuff like
like this like rc4
by the way don't use rc4 it was quite
popular 20 years ago but
today is not recommended given the
hypothetical situation here
let's say i can't pick my library and i
have to
pick an algorithm for something is that
where i want to look at some
type of standards like a nist standard
or like a fip
standard to kind of decide what the
appropriate amount of security is for my
data
yeah i think if you if you stick to the
nest uh recommendations and um
defeat series of standards uh usually
you're good to go because they
they follow pretty well um the last
you know the recent attacks and the
obsolete the
um the old insecure ciphers just such a
one
i think today most of the time you're
going to use aes as gcm
what's important is a mistake i see
quite often is people that just encrypt
stuff
who are there to encrypt and
authenticate the data
so if you can use augcm which will get
you
authenticity and integrity and knowledge
confidentiality
then you should be whether you encrypt i
don't know database content
or data or some some network
communication
uh you want to use aes gcm or cha cha
poly
which is another type of authenticated
cipher but
yeah most of the time you want to use
one of these standards and in terms of
hashing
you may also care about speed
performance uh
so small uh a small personal plug here
so i've designed a
blank screen with a number of other
people so blake's three is a hash
function
that is extremely fast if you have a
multi-core
and and simply um instructions so if you
care about speed
you might pick a different algorithm
than if you don't but um
black streak for example is considerably
faster than just three or so if you hash
large files you may want to give it a
try all right awesome and i'll include
some links and resources to some of the
libraries and the protocols that we
mentioned here
so just to start to wrap up the show
here what would be one takeaway
from this episode that a software
engineer should have uh
don't hush passport with a normal hash
function
and do not hardcore the nonsense
in your system that's maybe the most the
most
common bugs i i find and also
use authenticated encryption not just
encryption when you can
because it saves you a lot of problems
detecting corrupted data and um
preventing attackers from modifying your
data that's quite simple things
but when you're not a cryptographer you
you don't notice
so and maybe a last piece of advice if
you want to learn more about
cryptography
i heard there's a nice book called
serious cryptography which i happen to
be
the author of which kind of explains all
these concepts in relatively
simple terms yeah so i'll definitely
make sure to include your book in the
show notes and in the references section
just to kind of you know completely
close this out is there any further work
you're doing on the topic
well these days i'm working on a very
different kind of cryptography
that you find in blockchain applications
i'm interested in special signatures and
threshold
encryption whereby you have a multiple
parties
but you only need a subset of these
parties to collaborate to create a
signature or to decrypt
that that's really cool uh but that's
really for very specific applications
like what we find in a
in enterprise oneness um and i'm also
interested in post quantum cryptography
which is the kind of crypto that would
be safe against quantum computers but
we don't have pointed computers these
days but niece is working on standards
just in case uh
it happens yeah we didn't really talk
much about quantum crypto and quantum
safe and post quantum a lot in this
episode and maybe that'll be a topic for
another show
and now you're also working on a new
book is that correct yeah
that's right so that's a completely
different book than the last one
but it will be about explaining many
different concepts in cryptography from
the simplest one
to the most complex one this is some you
know historical
anecdotes so it could be another thing
uh later this year and
december probably with nostalgia press
i'm really excited about it
uh it will be kind of dictionary of
cryptography
that sounds awesome well jp i just want
to thank you for coming on the show and
discussing all these cryptography disc
topics and
encryption and hashing and all these
other things thanks justine that was a
really good discussion
uh we could have gone much longer but i
hope the how the podcast is most of it
and yeah see you next time see you next
time and i will definitely
include some social media resources in
case any of our listeners want to reach
out to you
excellent this is justin baier for
software engineering radio
thank you for listening thanks for
listening to sc radio an educational
program brought to you by ieee software
magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening